sixty minutes rewind no I always used to
say that being a comedian is a lot like
being a hooker I mean it's humiliating
and degrading but it only lasts 20
minutes and you do get $100 do you
remember your first appearance on The
Tonight Show oh sure sure March 7 1977 I
mean your first Tonight Show is kind of
like your first girl you know I mean
it's real fast it's over real quick you
weren't very good but you never forget
it but you do know you want to do it
again you know I know I'll do better the
next time what goes through your mind
when you look at welcome to your mind is
you realize there's not one joke on
there I would even tell today yet I told
them in front of 30 million people and
like President Bush throwing up in Japan
everybody hardly anyone saw Leno and a
handful of forgettable movies and
television pilots producers raved about
his talent but Helen Kushnick Leno's
longtime manager says he couldn't get
his own TV series mr. dark he was too
ethnic he was too menacing they actually
did tell me that they thought he'd be
frightening to children I know one
casting director said to me well you
know your jaw is too long he says what
we need to do is break it and then
rehang it I said well how long would
that take and he said well you probably
wouldn't be able to talk about a year
Jay and Mavis Nicholson who used to be a
comedy writer herself had been married
without children for 11 years
she says all those early rejections
forced him into an in strategy after
losing something that he came very close
to getting again on the basis that they
wanted somebody cuter it then came back
to us from various friends that they had
a cast and call out for this particular
part they were looking for a
good-looking Jay Leno and Jay said to me
at that time in this I really admired
him for this he said you know they
aren't gonna let me in the front door
it's I'm just gonna have to take a
little longer and come around the back
coming around the back man playing clubs
and college campuses from Omaha to
Orlando shaking hands signing autographs
even selling tickets he was like a
candidate running for office he averaged
300 days a year on the road
and he got famous one town at a time I
meet Santa Claus hello I feel a
blue-collar kid from Andover
Massachusetts he feels a little guilty
living by his wit I always sort of
respected people to work with their
hands people it was sort of fast talkers
are always the guy that people have
talked for a living didn't really seem
like they were really working to me
I mean when I was out here once I
remember I went down unemployment
because I hadn't had a job in a long
time I stood in line I get up to thing
and the guy said have you looked for
work and I said I I couldn't do it I
guess no I guess I didn't work hard
enough I'll come over here for an hour
in the morning an hour at night today
when Leno does relax it's likely to be
in his garage he used to have a day job
as a mechanic and has always loved cars
his interests and outlook maybe
blue-collar his collection of classic
cars and motorcycles is not which is one
indulgence most of my friends in
Hollywood have one car and 20 or 30
girlfriends and they're all broke see I
have one woman and all these cars and I
have a lot of money so actually this is
so much cheaper cheaper maybe but not
cheap
this 1931 Bentley one of his latest
acquisitions cost a half a million
dollars he's the investigative reporter
he's the comedian together they fight
crime on crafted Leno tonight this new
job you got hosting tonight's show
what kind of his job is hard job easy
job well it's not a real hard job I
don't think it's it but it's a 24-hour
day job it's kind of job I like it if I
get there at 2:30 we tape about 5:30 we
finishes 6:00 6:30 I'm home at 7:00
I'm fooling around the garage for now
and they come back in I write some jokes
fooling around the garage for an hour
then I meet with the writers about
midnight or so work till about 4:00 and
you only need four hours sleep I sleep
four hours maybe five not much more than
that it's not a lot of lifting involved
in this job someone does not get tired
particularly maybe not Jay Leno his
friends and fellow comics Jim Brogan and
ron Richards certainly do beginning at
midnight sitting around Leno's kitchen
table they start going over the next
night's monologue they're working with a
stack of 100 jokes written
by Leno and a staff of writers he keeps
around the country now they're looking
for the best 20 more economic news
series is laying off 7,000 ploys all
time if you don't seen one employee that
points it after deciding Leno reads them
an order into a tape recorder working on
the precise wording there's never
anybody working there it's 4:00 a.m. by
the time he gets to the joke about
turning the five-and-ten-cent store into
a 5 cent store Leno's getting you never
get run down and feel I'm tired you know
Alan can't used to have a joke that I
love said that he had gone into the
hospital for exhaustion he said boy is
that a rich man's disease you know you
don't see some guy in Pennsylvania been
digging coal for 30 years I'm tired so
don't get out of here you bum
exhausted you lazy get back in here that
shovel start thinking again and it's
true I mean it's a rich man's disease
exhaust if you have time to complain you
don't have enough work to do let's get
to the bottom of this the next day with
the monologue written Leno passes time
in his Tonight Show dressing room
hauling fans who have written in letters
usually complaining about one of his
jokes
oh I Nancy this is Jay Leno are most
people surprised when they pick up the
phone is Jay Leno I think so I think
they're surprised that you take the time
to give them a call
a lot of times people forget that they
wrote I called one woman and she go
that's my daughter she rides to every
crackpot
I said oh well thank you very much but
tell us a little oh that's interesting
mr. Donavan it's hard to get him off the
phone even when Tonight Show executive
producer Fred de Cordova stops by with
that night's rundown
Loggins notes you surprised me by
reading oh yes I want that will be as
soon as that happens I'll bring you down
some more even after five years of
sitting in for Johnny Leno is still
careful not to offend Parsons staff or
audience and in the process
some people think his humor has lost
some of its earlier bite some people
have said a few critics that since
you've started doing that Tonight Show
you've become a little bit more bland
yeah it's probably true
also don't forget I'm guest hosting on
someone else's show you know it might
open up a bit more when you when you go
out on your own
one thing Leno plans to tinker with and
sharpen up is the political humor
although politicians from Dan Quayle to
Bill Clinton find it sharp enough
already are you a Republican or a
Democrat I'm neither actually I'm
neither I try to remain the astonished
independent because every time I think
I'm a Republican they do something
greedy and every time I think I'm a
Democrat they do something stupid it's
difficult to imagine two people who were
more different than you and Johnny
Carson everyone says he's extremely
remote he's remote and people say that
maybe he is I don't know I can only
judge by what I see as a professional
sort of relationship that I have with
him and he's always been very gracious
but you don't have that many personal
conversations with him no no but I mean
I would feel funny you know like I say
hey what are we doing I mean it's a
different level economically and
socially and you know I don't know what
I would talk about unlike Johnny a
relaxed Leno goes out and fools around
with the audience 30 minutes before
showtime
do you feel a lot of pressure no but I
don't feel a lot of pressure or anything
I don't really worry about anything you
know my flood brush is like zero over
zero Japan says the US has no right to
tell Japan what to do hey sure we do the
customer's always right
most Sunday nights when we hope most
people are home watching television
Leno goes back on the road even if it's
the San Diego freeway he does just set
it the comedy and magic club in Hermosa
Beach just to stay in practice and to
try out new material
are you worried now that you're gonna be
in Beverly Hills 300 days a year that
you're I'm sure there people have a
bigger problem it's a terrible thing
yeah boy big brother is watching isn't
he can't make a move without this guy
you didn't believe they're everywhere
these people before we left town he
asked one last favor something he's
always wanted to do and since he humored
us we humored him yeah 60 minutes but I
don't nothing about that they oxen and a
baby phone we understand those asbestos
downtown shields I'm a bad company I saw
a long time I'm on look at that phony
meets them look it's a private home you
can't come in here look I don't know
about that meat snap that's all great